We have a lot of choices
to make about our diet.
Add to that, doing
the right thing
when it comes
to preventing
and treating a
chronic disease,
fighting a virus,
or losing weight,
and suddenly our
nutrition choices
can seem almost
overwhelming.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we take a look
at how some employers
are taking steps to help
us become healthier.
In our first story, we look at how
workplace wellness programs
report an average
ROI of 3,
returning $3 for
every $1 invested.
An impressive number of studies
have shown that lifestyle is
the root cause of what ails us,
particularly for chronic conditions.
The studies also show that
changing one’s lifestyle can have
a dramatic effect on
health improvement,
both in the prevention
and treatment of disease.
So, given the benefits of
lifestyle medicine interventions,
it would seem that our
health care system
would rush to embrace
this movement;
however, little could be
further from the truth.
Now, I know we have a
for-profit healthcare system,
but even just from a
dollars-and-cents perspective,
it may make sense—and dollars!
A majority of Americans have
health care insurance through their
employers, the cost for which
is rising at an alarming rate.
Health insurance premiums
continue to go up year after year.
Unfortunately, all the money
we’re spending has not translated
into healthier employees
or healthier Americans.
We spend more on
healthcare per person by far,
yet the U.S. population
is not healthy.
By 2014, our life expectancy had
slipped down to 43rd in the world.
And since then, our life
expectancy declined year after year.
It’s not just that other
countries are doing better,
we now may be living
shorter and shorter lives.
And unhealthier lives—again
even just from a financial
bottom-line perspective,
hundreds of billions
in productivity lost, beyond
all the healthcare costs.
One employee gets
diabetes, and it costs
about $10,000 more per year.
So, if a self-insured company
could prevent or reverse
that case, they could save
the company a lot of money,
raising the possibility
that workplace wellness programs
could not just be cost-neutral,
in other words pay for
themselves, but actually save
the company money, even
make the company money.
This brings up the concept of
ROI, or return on investment.
That’s how much money you get
back for every dollar spent.
So, an ROI of 3 to 1 means every
dollar you spend yields $3 back;
so, by investing in such a program
you’d end up tripling your money.
You don’t know though...
until you put it to the test.
Johnson & Johnson, for example,
claimed that investing
in employee wellness
yielded around 2 to 4 dollars
for each dollar they spent.
Citibank estimated their
return on investment
was $5 saved for every dollar spent.
A compilation of a handful of
such studies found an average ROI
of more than three dollars
of healthcare cost savings
for each dollar spent
on health promotion.
A more recent review including
more than 20 studies came up
with a return on investment
exceeding 5 to 1,
though an even more recent
review out of Harvard looking at
more than 30 studies found
the ROI closer to three dollars.
Spend one dollar, get
three back. Not a bad deal.
One heavy manufacturing company
reported an outstanding
34-to-1 return on investment,
and that’s just direct
healthcare costs.
Some of their indirect costs,
like lost workdays and disability,
fell even more.
Then, you can imagine other
potential benefits—happier employees,
more productive employees, making
them more likely to stick around.
So, do companies that
invest in health promotion
have a competitive advantage?
Publicly traded
companies that got
Corporate Health Achievement
Awards outperformed
the S&P 500 by 40 percent.
C. Everett Koop Award winners
outperformed the S&P 500 two to one.
Those scoring higher on workplace
health promotion best
practices, same trend.
And the same thing most
recently with companies
investing in an internal
culture of health.
Of course, instead of
healthier employees leading to
a more profitable company, maybe
more profitable companies
have more money to spend to
make employees healthier.
Is there a link between
stock market price growth
and having a great
employee wellness program?
Maybe, but correlation
doesn’t mean causation.
Maybe prioritizing
wellness is just a sign
of a great management team,
and that’s the real reason
they’re raking in the dough.
Even most of the ROI studies
lacked an adequate control group.
You can’t just compare the
costs of employees that signed up
versus those that didn’t,
because maybe healthier people
are just drawn to such
programs in the first place.
That’s why you need randomized
clinical trials to really
put it to the test,
which we’ll cover, next.
How much is a human life worth?
Ideally, we’d like to think
there is no price tag.
Each precious life is
of inestimable value,
but there are limited resources
and policy decisions to be made,
which leads to fascinating
papers like this:
the cost effectiveness of 500
life-saving interventions,
587 to be exact, with some costing
more than 10 billion dollars
per year of life saved.
Overall, the average
intervention costs $42,000,
which is how much it costs to
save a year of someone’s life
putting flashing lights
at railroad crossings.
So, how could you justify
not installing them?
Well, you could save more
lives with the same money
if you added grooved
pavement on highways.
But if you really cared about
saving drivers, you could save
nearly a hundred times more
lives investing the same money
in media campaigns to encourage
people to wear their seatbelts.
But if you really want value,
if you want to prevent
bangs for the least bucks,
there are some interventions
that save more resources
than they cost.
Yeah, most interventions cost
$10,000 or more per year
of life saved, but check out these.
Studies, for example, suggest
“Workplace Wellness Programs
Can Generate Savings.”
Not just saving more than
you’re spending but potentially
tripling your money
by investing in wellness.
But since employee participation
is almost always voluntary,
this introduces the
specter of selection bias,
where healthier people
are just drawn
to wellness programs
in the first place.
And indeed, during the year
prior to a wellness intervention,
those who would later
sign up already had lower
medical expenditures and
healthier behaviors
than future nonparticipants; so,
no wonder they could end up
doing better than their
nonparticipating colleagues
even if the wellness
program had zero benefit.
Thankfully, there are an
increased number of randomized
controlled trials of wellness
programs to see if we can prove
cause-and-effect, to
answer the question
“Do Workplace Health
Promotion Programs Work?,”
particularly important given that
the workplace wellness industry
is now a multibillion-dollar industry
One of the most recent
randomized controlled trials
was published in the Journal of the
American Medical Association.
Thousands of employees were
effectively randomized to a
workplace wellness program
at BJ’s Wholesale Club,
and although program
participants reported
they were engaging in more
positive health behaviors,
such as getting regular exercise,
there were no significant
differences in clinical measures
of health or health care
spending and utilization.
The authors suggested we may
have to temper our expectations
about the financial return on
investment that wellness programs
can deliver, at least
in the short term.
Now, some argue that even a
break-even program, that is,
one that does not impose
additional costs to the company
but produces signiﬁcant
population health improvement,
might be a worthy investment, but
perhaps the growing evidence
that demonstrates limited or
no concrete wellness program
effects should encourage wellness
companies and employers
to critically assess the programs
and try to improve them.
In a survey of 162 company
wellness programs, for example,
only a third offered
nutrition counseling.
And even with counseling,
it’s more than simply trying
to convince people to take
better care of themselves.
It requires that the organization
creates an environment
where leading a healthy lifestyle
is the “default” option.
What are they promoting in the
company cafeteria, for example?
What’s being served up at meetings
and in vending machines?
Yeah, a lifestyle management
program at PepsiCo failed to save
the company money, but somehow
I doubt one of the components
of PepsiCo’s wellness program,
Healthy Living, was telling
employees not to eat or drink
any of their own products.
In fact, if you go back
to that BJ’s case,
yes, a few percentages
more employees said
they were more regularly exercising,
but when it came to nutrition,
it was a complete flop,
in terms of things like
drinking less soda
or more fruits and vegetables.
No wonder their health hardly budged.
In a systematic review of
systematic reviews on the
effectiveness of dietary
workplace interventions,
the average improvement in
fruit and vegetable intake
combined was 0.7 portions a day.
No wonder these programs
aren’t doing better.
In Wealth of Nations, Adam Smith
wrote that workers
are less likely to be productive
“when they are frequently sick
than when they are
generally in good health.”
Sickness “cannot fail to diminish
the produce of their industry.”
Maybe they just need more produce
than 0.7 servings a day.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my latest book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
Or go to your local public
library for that matter.
For recipes, check out
my new “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books
goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.